My name is Catherine Coleman Flowers.
I am the founder of the Alabama Center
for Rule Enterprise,
and our work is primarily in Lawrence
County, Alabama,
between Selma and Montgomery,
which is where I'm from.
When I moved back to Alabama in 2000,
I saw that in rural communities,
especially my own community, people
were living with raw sewage on the ground,
and I just didn't think that that
should be the case at this point in time.
And a lot of these communities,
there was no investment
and no infrastructure.
So when people flush the toilet, the raw
sewage is going out on top of the ground.
It's called street paving
for people who have been arrested,
who could not afford site septic systems.
And we found that those systems don't work
either.
They still failed.
But I'm talking about something
as basic as flushing the toilet
and not being able
to see it in your front yard.
No one has acknowledged
the lack of infrastructure investment
in rural communities,
especially for rural communities
in the Black
Belt region of the United States.
And I'm finding out that this is true
of rural communities around the country.
Those
are the issues that we should resolve,
though,
in the first half of the last century,
when we had the Rockefeller Sanitary
Commission trying to eliminate hookworm
in the United States,
but in these communities, they have always
been victims of hyper inequality.
It still exists, and it's getting worse.
It's in the intersection
of this type of injustice
with sewage on the ground,
and it's getting warmer.
The possibility of illnesses
that we've never seen before,
a cropping or illnesses
they simply don't test for
because they assume that this is a problem
in third world nations around the world.
But we actually have those kinds
of conditions undergirded by inequality
here in this country.
And climate change
is going to make the situation worse.
I got engaged and had to find partners
and collaborators
that can help us solve this problem.
First of all, stop the health department
from arresting people in Lawrence County.
And then the second part of it,
which is defining technological solutions
that will work.
What we've
done is launch a wastewater challenge.
We have engaged universities, Baylor's
National School of Tropical Medicine
as part of that collaborative.
We're about to publish a study with Baylor
where we found
evidence of tropical diseases
in lands County.
And before we start promoting technologies
whole heartedly, we want to test.
And that's our next phase.
Duke University
is part of that collaboration.
We're just hoping that foundations
that fund these kinds of efforts around
the world
will start looking inward as well,
and fund a wastewater
challenge here in this country.
I think the first step is get engaged,
be involved.
I think democracy doesn't work
when people are not informed.
A lot of people don't know what's going on
in their communities if they know
what's going on, how their representatives
are voting, who's funding them.
I think that
that would make a big difference.
I think there are a number of things
they can do.
People don't have to do what I do.
There's so many things that are
needed in the communities.
My story may be different
from others
because I grew up with activist parents
in the movement for the right to vote
in the 1960s, and there were people
who are now historical figures
that were regulars at our home.
So I always felt that
if change had to occur, that
I have to be on the part of the solution,
not a part of the problem.
The fact that I grew up poor
in a rural community, and I'm here
being able to lift up voices of people
from my community and find solutions.
I think if I can do it, and faced
with the type of inequality
as an African-American female
in this country, anyone can do it.